On the 31st of August 2025, Czech
railways celebrated a breakthrough. The
first ever regular domestic intercity
train service at a speed of 200 km per
hour between Prague and Budweis. This
was achieved through years of track
upgrades, straightenings, and
realignments. Journey times on the line
between Prague and Budweis are thus
shorter than ever to the point where it
makes more sense to take the train than
to drive. This is 21st century rail
supposedly. Pendolino higher speed EMUs
breaking the glass ceiling of 160 km per
hour top speeds blasting across the
landscape at 200 just like in the west.
But as impressive this achievement is,
it's almost completely meaningless and
misses the point of a quality rail
service. And in my opinion, increasing
the regular speed to 200 was a mistake.
It should have been left at 160. Now
hold on a minute. You could say, I
thought trains were meant to compete
with the car. Don't you want trains to
go as fast as possible to decrease
journey times, thus making rail more
appealing? Well, yes, I do want rail to
be as appealing as possible, and I do
want to decrease journey times, but past
a point, a sheer increase in speed is
rarely a solution. Sacrilege, I know.
Why don't I want trains to go faster?
Well, I do, but not at all costs and not
above other considerations. In today's
world, speed fetishism is largely a tech
bro thing. We all remember the Hyperloop
promising 1,000 plus kilometers per hour
top speeds in vacuum tunnels before it
came to light that it was just a scam to
defund California highspeed rail. Or
there is Neommo, well was promising to
retrofit existing infrastructure for a
whopping 550 km/h. They will do this or
would have done this by putting some
sort of magnetic parallel track into
existing tracks so their pod shaped like
a futuristic sex toy can go real fast on
it. Yeah, right. But such projects or
rather the tech pros behind them do not
understand how rail is supposed to work
for them. It's just faster, faster and
more faster. Speed is everything. Big
number means big good. So keep
increasing that easily marketable metric
and keep that sweet venture capital
flowing. In reality, once your rail
service can reliably operate at the 140
160 km/h baseline, speed suddenly
becomes far less relevant. And the Swiss
understand this very well. The Godard
base tunnel is an absolutely monstrous
piece of infrastructure, a higher speed
rail tunnel under the Alps, 57
kilometers long. Aside from a brief
episode of Italian state terrorism where
the tunnel was clogged by wine, tomato
sauce, and spaghetti, it has been in
stable operation for about a decade,
cutting the journey times of gear rail
lines by 1 hour. It is nothing short of
a revolution in local and international
rail travel. Well, hold on now, sir. I
thought speed wasn't that important. And
now you're applauding the Godard base
tunnel for reducing journey times by an
hour. Well, yes and yes. But inside the
Godard base tunnel, something very
interesting is happening which other
rail operators would do well to
replicate. Let me [music] explain. A
train journey usually has multiple
components. People don't just teleport
onto the train, ride the train, then
teleport to their destination from the
arrival station. It's a complex process.
Let's look at a personal example.
Suppose I'm sitting around in Prague's
castle district [music] sipping my €13
draft PSN from a giant one liter glass,
which is not actually draft PSN, but
cheap beer from a pet bottle, the kind
you usually find at the bottom of the
shelf, which the bartender dumps into
your glass while you're not looking and
then bills you out €13. One liter of
that beer costs 90s at Tesco, by the
way. Welcome to Prague, everybody. So,
I'm sitting around enjoying my 13 pet
bottle beer. Its aroma reminding me of
3:00 a.m. shirtless brawls in a little
parking lot. As I savor the taste, I'm
suddenly overcome by the urge to visit
one of the smaller towns around Budweis.
Hopefully, it has a little [music] for
reasons. So, I decide to travel there. I
walk down to the metro station and
travel to Prague main station. Metro
frequencies are high enough so that I
don't have to worry about planning my
trip in advance. and I make it just in
time to catch that incredible 200 km per
hour intercity service in the form of
the Pendolino, the flagship rolling
stock of Czech railways, a 23 years old
higher speed electric multiple unit or
EMU of which they own a grand total of
six. They used to have seven, but they
wrecked two of them and could only
restore one. So, uh, yay Pendolino
question mark. Still, this is the train
that breaks the glass ceiling of speed,
propelling me to Budweis [music] at 200
km/h. Oh, Jesus. What is this? It
wobbles. All right, because it's a
tilting train. Now, okay, look, I like
these trains. They are nice. But because
of the tilting design, the carriages
have to have these weird sloped walls so
the frame doesn't accidentally catch
anything while it's tilted. But this
results in a cramped interior with
barely any overhead luggage space. And
even the second class has to have a two
plus one seat arrangement instead of the
regular 2 plus two. Compared to Czech
railways first generation railjet
trains, the Pendolino can thus seat a
100 people [music] less, which is quite
a problem considering the chronic lack
of Czech railways train capacity on
their long-distance lines. Because of
its exotic design and characteristics,
the train is not allowed into any other
country except Slovakia. It could
technically go to Austria, but they're
not really keen on having it there. Not
since rail jets are a thing. But hey,
now the Pentalino goes to Budweis as
well, right on the brand new 200 kmph
track. Well, this is where the skull
duggery starts. The tracks to Budwise
were indeed straightened and they did a
great job except the track speed is not
200 km/h. It's 185. Now, the Pentalino
can travel at 200 there despite that
limit because it's a tilting train. So
great, we still managed to achieve 200
through the power of technology. Well,
yeah. on one train per day per
direction. One out of 25 daily
connections, one of them travels at 200
km/ hour instead of 185 outside peak
hours. That is not much to put it very
extremely mildly. No matter celebrations
were held, photo ops were performed.
Chromo material was waved in front of
cameras commemorating the first 200 km/h
intercity service in Czecha. It goes
once a day, late at night, and only if
there is a tilting fan available. And it
will save you 4 minutes. Incredible. As
of September 2025, not once did it
manage to arrive on time, by the way.
But hey, now Czech railways can
technically say that they have reached
200 km/h in regular service. And the
Czech rail administration can brag about
their first 200 km/h line. some segments
of it. Tilting trains only once a day at
night when the weather is nice. But all
that is still not the worst thing about
this PR stunt because as I'm sitting on
the pendalino on my way to Budweis
zooming past the landscape at incredible
speeds, I am not at ease. I am not
happy. I am nervous. I keep glancing at
the information screen. But instead of
the big shiny 200 km/h sign, my eyes are
fixated at the top right corner. That's
where the clock is. See, in Budweis, I
will have 10 minutes to transfer to my
connection. If I miss it, I'll be forced
to wait an hour for the next connection.
But getting off this cramped train takes
time. Orienting myself at the station
takes time. Finding my connecting train
takes time. This means if anything
[music] happens along the way, any
stoppage, problem, issue, any small
delay will immediately put my transfer
at risk. And so now my entire evening is
up in the air. Will I make it to my
destination on time? Or will I be forced
to waste an hour of my life at the
station? What will I even do there? Down
a pet bottle beer and find a little
parking lot? Ah, isn't nature beautiful?
A majestic battle between two
omniinkrinkers. We should cherish and
protect such natural behavior, including
outside little parking lots and our
cities. This is where Planet Wild comes
in. A community-f funed reing
organization with whom I partnered for
today's video. Planet Wild is a
worldwide community of 15,000 plus
people who want to help preserve our
biosphere. They engage in various
community funded missions such as
reforestation, ocean floor cleanup, and
more. They support a different project
each month and document their
accomplishments for the whole world to
see right here on YouTube. For example,
a project they launched in May 2025 is
the cleaning up of one of the most
polluted rivers in Europe located in
Albania to prevent it from reaching the
Mediterranean Sea. A total of €100,000
have been invested with the mission
including a waste management plant
converted from an old Soviet era
factory. This project and more like it
are made possible by People's Monthly
contributions. Think of this as nature's
Patreon. Basically, results of Planet
Wild's work are regularly posted on
their YouTube channel and they even have
an app if you prefer. It's because of
this transparency that I am glad to be a
member. You can give any amount that
feels right to you. So, if you would
like to join Planet Wild's community and
contribute to their missions, check out
the link in the description or use the
QR code on the screen. The first 100
people to join with my code Adam will
get the first month for free covered by
me. And don't worry, you can cancel
anytime. Thank you for checking out
Planet Wild and thanks to Planet Wild
for sponsoring today's video. So, will I
catch my connection in Budweis? I have
no idea. Also, after getting off my
connecting train, I wanted to catch the
last bus, which would take me to my
final destination. But if the Pendolino
misses this connecting train, the next
one departing in an hour will not have a
connecting bus. So now I also have to be
on the phone with my relative who lives
there. Hi, I'm sorry to bother you.
Listen, if I don't make my connection,
could you please come pick me up at the
station by car? Yeah, because the last
bus leaves an hour before that. All
right, thanks a lot. I'll let you know
in an hour. Okay, bye. And so now it's
not just my schedule that's up in the
air, but also my relatives. Because the
Pendolino's schedule is so stretched
right to the absolute breaking point
that even the smallest hiccup will
immediately cause a delay it cannot work
down. Its schedule basically has no
reserve. All because they wanted to
decrease travel time on paper at all
costs [music] because this 200 km/h
service must be faster than the regular
connections. This is compounded by the
issue that the Pendalino is a quarter of
a century old rolling stock which cannot
accelerate well. As such, it needs 2 and
1/2 minutes to reach [music] 200 km/h.
Modern rolling stock like the Toddlis,
which is a double-decker, mind you, only
needs about 50 seconds. And this is why
despite all the fanfare, the bragging,
the tilting tech, all that, that 200
km/h intercity service is basically
pointless. Meanwhile, regular service on
the line is quite good. Regular trains
[music] can still travel there at 185
kilometers per hour, which is cool, but
Czech railways was craving that sweet PR
treat of the nice round number of 200.
So, here we are. This is the issue with
this techbro attitude of speed above
all. Make the easily marketable number
bigger. That should improve things.
Well, actually, past a point, it won't.
[music] It may even make things worse.
And the Swiss understand this. So, the
Godard base tunnel, an absolutely
monstrous piece of infrastructure, so
deep that without ventilation, some
sections would have an ambient
temperature of 46° C due to the
geothermal gradient. And here's the
thing about it. The tracks in it were
built for 230 km/h. However, the trains
travel intentionally slower, only at
200. If there is a delay if there is
some sort of hiccup, issue, whatever,
then the train accelerates to 230 km/h
in order to work down its delay. So if
the train enters the tunnel with a
5-minute delay, when it emerges, it will
only have a twominut delay. The Godard
base tunnel essentially eats train
delays. So instead of pushing the
schedule, thus the operational speed, to
their absolute limit, the Swiss took a
step back and intentionally set speeds
lower so they [music] can use that speed
buffer to help eliminate delays. Having
sections like these on your network act
as schedule stabilizers, and this can be
done even at lower speeds, like if you
have a track for 160, but your schedule
is designed around 140. So if you're
delayed, you can accelerate to 160 and
work it down. Because above a certain
threshold, passengers don't care how
fast a train goes. All they care about
is a consistent reliable service they
can plan on top of. You can have the
fastest connection in the world, but if
you cannot operate it reliably, and
passengers miss their connections left
and right, leading to complications,
headache, and wasted time, then it's
basically worthless. It's like, yeah,
great. The journey time is low and the
speed is high on paper, but grandma took
too long to board, so I missed my
connection. So now I have to sit here
for an additional hour watching a
shirtless brawl in front of the station.
And so if I take a Swiss railways train,
let's say from Constance all the way
down to Lugano, I will have to transfer
twice. To do so, I'll have 20 minutes in
Turik and 14 minutes in Arth Guldau. And
I will easily manage both of them
because trains are overwhelmingly
punctual because the schedule and
infrastructure were made with reserves
in mind ensuring operational
reliability. This results in a
punctuality of 93.2% 2% and importantly
a connection punctuality of 98.7%.
In Switzerland, you will catch your
connection 987 times out of 1,000. And
as far as regular passengers are
concerned, this metric is far more
important than chasing magical top speed
numbers. So, Swiss trains don't go full
speed unless they have to, and their
rail system is better off for it. And so
are Swiss passengers. Thank you for
watching, and don't forget to check out
Planet Wild. You can watch their mission
cleaning up Europe's most polluted river
over here. If you like my content,
please consider supporting me on Patreon
or become a channel member here on
YouTube. Besides helping me make more
content for you, you also get adfree
early access to all videos that I put
out. And with that, I'll be seeing you
next time.